[{"question":"<p><strong>Structural unemployment is mainly caused by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Seasonal variations","Changes in production techniques","Changes in the demand pattern of an economy","Shortage of information about job opportunities"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>The total money values of all goods and services produced in a country during a certain period is measured using the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Income method","Expenditure method","Output method","Factor method"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>The loans from the World Bank to developing countries are mainly to support<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The establishment of more universities","Capital intensive technology","Their low level of consumption","Infrastructural investments"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>Fiscal policy is the government&rsquo;s plan to control aggregate demand by manipulating<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Revenue and expenditure","The demand and supply of money","Tastes and preferences of consumers","The structure of production and employment"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>A commodity will be demanded only if<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Consumers income increases","It has no close substitutes","The price is low","It has utility"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>If P = &frac12; (Qs + 15). What is the quantity supplied at N9.00?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1.5","3.0","12.0","33.0"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>A public liability company is run on a daily basis by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The chief executive","The shareholders","The board of directors","Financial consultants"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>The term balance of trade can be defined as the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Relation between value of exports and value of imports over a given period of time","Balance owed to the rest of the world in payment for imports","Price paid for imports in terms of exports","Relation between payments of all kind made by a country to the rest of the world over a given period of time."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main function of price mechanism is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Limit consumer demand","Enable producers make profit","Allocate scarce resources among competing needs","Ensure consumer sovereignty"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>Average Fixed Cost is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Average Total Cost less the sum of Average Variable Cost","Half the sum of all costs","Total Fixed Cost divided by the level of output","Total Fixed Cost plus Marginal Cost"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a good is an inferior good, then<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is also necessarily a Giffen good","The quantity of the good demanded varies inversely with its price","Its income elasticity of demand is negative","The poor buy the good only out of habit"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>The Law of Diminishing Returns begins to operate when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total product begins to rise","Total product begins to fall","Marginal product begins to fall","Marginal product begins to rise"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the dangers of the localization of industries is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Residual unemployment","Mass unemployment","Cyclical unemployment","Structural unemployment"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a government wants to reduce the level of inflation, it will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Run a budget surplus","Run a budget deficit","Run a balanced budget","Borrow more money"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>An issue of bank-notes not backed by gold but by government securities is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Fiduciary issue","Guaranteed money","Seigniorage","Legal tender"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>The effect of emigration on a country&rsquo;s population all other things remaining equal is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Increase its size","Cause overpopulation","Increase its growth rate","Reduce its size"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The elasticity of supply of perishable goods is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Elastic","Zero","Inelastic","Unitary"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the cost of production for a firm continues to increase as its output rises, the firm is said to be experiencing<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Large scale production","Profit maximization","Economies of scale","Dis-economies of scale"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The primary problem of economics is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["To obtain a more equitable distribution of money income","Production of a given output with the lowest cost combination of factors of production","Adoption of capital-intensive technology","Increasing the quantity of the fixed factor of production"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic principles of co-operative societies are those of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Active participation of capitalists in the affairs of co-operative societies","Workers ownership and worker control","Sole proprietorship","Partnership"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In estimating the national income of a country, the three approaches usually adopted are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Expenditure, value-added and output","Income, final product and output","Expenditure, income and output","Avoidance of double counting, final expenditure and value-added"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The natural growth rate of a population is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sum of the birth rate and the death rate","Sum of the birth rate and the net migration","Birth rate minus death rate","Birth rate divided by net migration"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The role of the central bank of Nigeria in the economic development of Nigeria is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Use cheques and bank drafts to facilitate business transactions","Maintain a stable price system","Give short and medium term loans to the public","Give financial and technical advice to customers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Localization of industries refers to the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Tendency to concentrate industries in particular areas","Siting of industries in certain areas","Deliberate policy of influencing location of industries generally","Zoning of industries"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>GDP differs for GNP because GDP<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Is inclusive of depreciation","Emphasizes the final goods and services produced within the country at a particular period","Emphasizes the goods and services produced within the country","Emphasizes the market value of all final goods and services produced by nationals"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>At any given level of output, the total cost of a firm equals the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal cost plus the average cost","Fixed cost less its variable cost","Average cost multiplied by its output","Economic costs multiplied by variable cost"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If two commodities are good substitutes for one another, an increase in the demand for one will reduce the demand for the other. This type of demand is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Composite demand","Elastic demand","Competitive demand","Inelastic demand"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>As long as marginal utility is positive, the total utility must be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Negative","Increasing","Zero","Decreasing"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Inductive method of scientific reasoning involves<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Drawing conclusions from specific to general","Making inferences based on theory","Using past to explain the present","Drawing conclusions from general to specific"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The ability of commercial banks to create money depends on the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Reserve ratio","Liquidity ratio","Interest rate","Capital base"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given that the total cost is 1000, total variable cost is 2500 and the output 100 units. The average cost of producing one unit is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["60","45","35","30"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The table below gives the market demand schedule for commodity X<\/strong><br \/><strong>Price (N) Quantity (million units)<\/strong><br \/><strong>60 100<\/strong><br \/><strong>50 140<\/strong><br \/><strong>40 220<\/strong><br \/><strong>30 260<\/strong><br \/><strong>20 300<\/strong><br \/><strong>10 340<\/strong><br \/><strong>If the price of a commodity X falls from N40.00 to N30.00, what is the price elasticity of demand?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.62","0.73","1.00","1.50"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>In estimating the national income of a country, the three approaches usually adopted are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Expenditure, value-added and output","Income, final product and output","Expenditure, income and output","Avoidance of double counting, final expenditure and value-added"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The value of the multiplier depends on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["MPC and a level of income","Level of personal income","Level of personal savings","Government policy and MPC"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Contractionary monetary policy is used to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Control inflation","Bridge the deflationary gap","Expand the output level","Deregulate the economy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>At any given level of output, a firm&rsquo;s total variable cost equals<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total cost less marginal cost","Total cost less total fixed cost","Total cost less average cost","Average variable cost and marginal variable cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the most important factors that should be considered in the location of an industry is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Nearness to the financial centre","Assured patronage by government functionaries","Availability of inputs and market","Availability of adequate security"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>In economics analysis, a statement is said to be normalize if it<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Relates to value judgment","Is contradictory","Is incorrect","Can be tested scientifically."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The degree of specialization is limited by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal cost exceeding marginal revenue","Extent of the market","Availability of specialized skills and machinery","Disadvantage of standardization."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these statements describes a mixed economy?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The government and the private sector interact in solving the basic economic problems","The invisible hand solves the basic economic problems","The government produces and distributes all goods and services","Society answers the question \u0093what\u0094, \u0093why\u0094 and for \u0093whom\u0094 questions only through the market system."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the financial institutions is charged with the formulation of monetary policies in Nigeria?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The Lagos state stock exchange","The Nigeria deposit insurance corporation","The Central Bank of Nigeria","The Abuja commodity exchange."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The primary function of non-banking financial institutions is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Manage investment portfolios for government","Mobilize saving for investment","Grant loans to banks","Receive deposits from banks."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given that beef and fish are substitutes, a rise in the price of beef relative to that of fish will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Induce greater demand for beef","Induce greater demand for fish","Induce lower demand for fish","Equate demand for beef and fish."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main function of price mechanism is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ensure consumer sovereignty","Enable producers make profits","Allocate scarce resources among compelling ends","Limit consumer demand."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Production in Economics can be defined as the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Totality of producing, buying and consuming.","Transformation of raw material and services in order to provide ultimate utility.","Transformation of raw materials and services in order to make maximum profits.","Production of goods and services for consumption."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given that the cash reserve ratio is 10 percent, what is the maximum amount of money that the banking system can create from an initial cash deposit of #1000.00?<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["#100.00","#1,000.00","#9,000.00","#10,000.00"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given that the cash reserve ratio is 10 percent, what is the maximum amount of money that the banking system can create from an initial cash deposit of #1000.00?<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["#100.00","#1,000.00","#9,000.00","#10,000.00"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most important economic characteristic differentiating commercial banks from other financial institutions is their<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Functions as a safe and profitable store place for savings","Role in financing balance of payments deficits","Status as an intermediary between savers and borrowers","Ability to create and destroy money."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given that Y= C + I and C = bY where b = 0.08, what is the multiplier?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["5","10","4","2"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The difference between payments and receipts for visible trade is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Bilateral trade","Current balance","balance of payment","balance of trade."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A free trade area emerges when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Traders from one part of the country can move freely to other- parts","Customs regulations are harmonized among countries","A group of countries decide to remove restriction on imports from one another","The UNCTAD is in force."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Population density refers to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Densely populated urban centre","The total area divided by the total population","Densely populated rural areas","The total population divided by the total area."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>An aspect of taxation that involves normative economics is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Tax rate","Effect on incentive to work","Fairness of the tax","Tax burden"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A tax that increases at a higher percentage as income increases is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A proportional tax","A regressive tax","A progressive tax","An income tax"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the assumptions of ordinary utility in consumer behavior is that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Consumer are irrational","Marginal utility rises continuously","Utility is measureable","Utility can be ranked."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the normal channel of distribution the&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>breaking of bulk is performed by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Producer.","Wholesaler.","Retailer.","Consumer."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the most outstanding disadvantage of cooperative societies as business organization is that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["True spirit of cooperation is marred by delegated authority","Members show much interest","It is poorly financed","Membership interest is centered on sharing of essential commodities."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A disadvantage of joint - stock company is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Unlimited liability","Limited liability","Continuity","Loss of controlling interest"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A characteristics of a debenture is that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Its yield is based on profits","Its yield is a fixed rate of interest","It has a redemption date","There is a voting when interest is paid"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following situations can give rise to economic problems?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Unlimited human wants","Wants of varying importance","Limited means available for satisfying wants","Means used in different ways."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main objective of the economic community of West African state is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Establish a West African development bank","Create a West African army","Introduce a common currency for the sub region","Promote the free movement of persons, goods and services within the sub \u0096 region"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In international trade, shipping and other freight&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>charges are treated as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Invisible items","Unilateral transfers","Capital transactions","Autonomous capital transactions."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A situation in which a commodity sold abroad below its cost of production in the home country&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Dumping","Counter trade","Bilateral trade","Trade liberalization"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The borrowing rights of a member country of the international monetary fund are determined by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Its balance of payment position","Its quota to the fund","The size of its gold reserve."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>An increase in money supply, other things being equal, will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Lower interest rates","Reduce income","Ensure trade balance","Increase money demand."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Two principal ways by which banks can lend money to their customers are through<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Loans and overdrafts.","Loans and discounting bills.","Overdrafts and cheques.","Overdraft and treasury bills."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>An increase in the discount rate is an indication of a central bank intension to pursue<\/strong><\/p>","options":["An expansionary monetary policy","A disciplined money policy","A dynamic monetary policies","A contractionary monetary policy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm is in its optimum size when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It produces the greatest output at the minimum cost","It has a motive to increase output","Marginal cost equals marginal revenue","Marginal cost is less than marginal revenue."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm achieves least cost in production by substituting factors until<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Their factor prices are equal","Their marginal-physical products are each equal to their factor prices","Their marginal-physical- product are each zero","The ratio of their marginal \u0096 physical-product equals the ratio of their prices."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is the real cost of satisfying any want in the sense of the alternative that has to be&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>foregone?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Variable cost","Opportunity cost","Total cost","Prime cost."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Scarcity in economics means that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Human wants are limitless","The economy can scarcely produce anything","Resources are limited in relation to want","The economy has very few resources."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economics is often described as a science&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>because<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It uses scientific methods to explain observed phenomena and predict future events","It makes the use of field work","It makes use of controlled experiments","Laboratory experiments that are performed."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is an important function of prices in a market economy?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ensuring that resources are used in the most efficient manner","Ensuring an equitable distribution of goods and services","Ensuring that all industries are perfectly competitive in the long run","Equating level of purchases in the level of needs."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the history of economic thought, the concept of division of labor is usually associated with<\/strong><\/p>","options":["David Ricardo","JM Keynes","Adam Smith","Karl Marx"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the operation of market forces, the market is in equilibrium at the point where<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Demand and supply curves intersect in more than one point provided the market is cleared","The excess in the market can be convenient stored","Excess demand is negative","Demand and supply curves incorrect."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A shift in demand curve for a commodity when the supply curve is vertical will lead to change in&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Price only","Quantity only","Quality only","Price and quantity."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>T<\/strong><strong>he difference between personal income and personal disposable income is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Personal income tax","Investment income","Personal savings","Consumption expenditure."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The Malthusian theory of population growth is often said to be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Oversimplified","Ambiguous","Optimistic","Pessimistic.."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Labor productivity is defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Output per man \/hour","Average output","The minimum number of hours worked","Total level of output."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Efficiency of labor is enhanced by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Involvement in own family affairs","War against indiscipline","Mechanization processes","Improved working condition and training."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Devaluation helps in checking adverse balance of payments if the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Demand for imports is elastic","Demand for imports is inelastic","Supply of exports is elastic","Demand for exports is inelastic."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Gains from trade depends on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Comparative advantage","Absolute advantage","Distribution cost advantage","Absolute cost advantage."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Favorable terms of trade is important to a country because it facilitates<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Economic prosperity for importers and exporters","Export of hard currency by the government","Economic prosperity for the country","Absolute cost advantage."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The tax takes an increasing fractional of income as income goes down is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Conditional","Regressive","Progressive","Proportional."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A greater burden of the taxes on essential goods is borne by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Higher income group.","Newly recruited workers.","Lower income workers.","Contract work."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The effect of an increase in the personal income tax is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Raise the absolute price level","Distort the economy","Reduce unemployment","Reduce the disposable income."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most important advantage of cooperative societies is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Their high degree of democracy","The increase in the cost of marketing","That members are encouraged to save money","The possibility of raising loans for the members."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a public company, shares are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sold to one person only","Distributed freely","Advertised to members of the public for subscription","Disposed off by the chief executive"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is a characteristic of the private limited liability company?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Its shares can be sold to the public","The number of share holders ranges from 50 to 100","All share holders have equal powers and responsibilities","The number of shareholders ranges from 2 to 50."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>An important function for the retailer is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Grant credit to the wholesaler","Break bulk and sell products in small units","Reduce cost of distribution","Generate demand for product through advertisement"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main handicap of sole proprietorship is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Limited liability","Lack of technical know \u0096 how","Low profit margin","Inadequate capital"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The type of business organization mostly used for producing public goods in Nigeria is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sole proprietorship","Limited liability companies","Cooperative societies","Statutory corporations"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The types of business finance that entitles the holder to fixed rate of dividend is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Preferred stock","Common stock","Debenture","Bank loan"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A debenture share entitles its holder to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Participate in the annual general meeting of the company","Share in the dividend declared","Receive a fixed interest on sums invested","Doard of directors."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Tariffs on imports are meant to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Prevent a country from becoming a dumping ground for foreign goods","Discourage exports","Encourage exports","Increase the level of external dependency"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a country has a balance of payment crisis, which of the following measures can best bring about an improvement in the short run?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Large \u0096 scale importation on foreign goods","Investments in capital market abroad","Large \u0096 scale export of locally made goods","Repayment of debt to her creditors."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The terms of trade of a country is defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Index of import price\/index of export price x 100","Index of exportation\/Index of importation x 100","Index of visible imports\/Index of visible exports x 100","Index of export prices\/ Index of import prices x 100"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the gains by member states of the Economic community of West African states is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Monoculture dependency","Trade creation","Trade inversion","Economic independency"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Deflation is a persistent fall in the general price level and is usually caused by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A reduction in total demand.","An increase in government spending.","An increase in the money supply.","An increase in aggregate demand."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Price can be defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A rate of exchange","A medium of exchange","The cost of a product","The standard of accounting."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Money market differs from capital market in that it<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Uses interest rate while capital market does not","Is limited in scope while capital market is not","Deals with money only while capital market  deals with capital as well","Deals with short - term loan while capital market deals with long- term funds"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The ultimate objective of economics is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Make the best use of scarce resources","Decide under what circumstances in the economy","Organize production at the lowest cost","Make effort to understand how the economy works"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>What to produce in any society is determined by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Competition among different producer","Competition among different consumers","Supply and demand in the factor market","Expenditure of the people on different commodities"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the fundamental differences between a capitalist and a socialist economy is that while<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The former is characterized by complete government ownership of resources, the latter  is characterized by complete private ownership","In the former, price s act as signals in the  allocation of resources, it is the central authority that perform this function in the latter","Taxes are levied in a capitalist economy, there  is no taxation in a socialist economy","Income and wealth are equally distributed in the socialist economy, this is not so in a capitalist economy."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>If at #50 per kg. 1000kg of yam were purchased and at #30 per kg, 1500kg were purchased, the&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>resultant point elasticity of demand is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A. 2","1.25","0.00125","1000"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>If as the price of a commodity rises, the quantity demanded of the commodity remains the same,&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>then the demand for the commodity is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Infinitely elastic","Static","Perfectly inelastic","Externally determined"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic development may be defined as economic growth<\/strong><\/p>","options":["In a given country","Over a long period","And improved health facilities","And improved distribution of wealth."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the price of ball point pen falls from #20 to #15 and the quantity demanded increases from 200 to 300 the point elasticity of demand is equal to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2","1.25","0.5","4"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the price elasticity of a certain commodity is less than unity, then<\/strong><\/p>","options":["An increase in the price of the commodity will raise the total revenue of the producer","An increase in price leaves the total revenue unchanged","A decrease in price raises the total revenue of the supplier","A decrease in price leaves the total revenue constant"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Frictional Unemployment<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Is total unemployment minus structural","Occurs when the unemployed are persons with specific training","Occurs when the number of job seekers exceeds the number of vacancies","Occurs when people are changing jobs."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The Nigerian Bank for commerce and industry<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A commercial bank","A development bank","An industrial bank","A merchant bank"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>To control inflation, the monetary authorities of a country can<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Reduce taxes","Advice government to increase its expenditure","Engage in expansive monetary policy","Engage in restrictive monetary policy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is used by the central bank to control the rate of interest?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Bill of exchange","Fixed deposit account","Open market operation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>An increasing population might be of economic benefit to a country if<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The female population is greater than the male population","The dependency ratio is increasing as the a continuously total population","A continuously higher proportion falls into the working class category","The rural and urban proportions are balanced"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The demands made on each other by the agricultural and industrial sectors as the economy grows are reflected in<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Backward and forward linkages","Horizontal and vertical linkages","Vertical linkages functional linkage","Functional linkage"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A corporation can obtain funds by issuing bonds. A bond is a form of debt which falls due for&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>repayment after<\/strong><\/p>","options":["6 months","9 months","2 years","10 or more years."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The age distribution of a population is NOT<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>influenced by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Birth rates","Death rates","School leaving age"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The tax that takes an increasing fractional of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>income as income goes down is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Conditional","Regressive","Progressive","Proportional"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Unlike the retailer, the wholesaler provides<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Useful information to the manufacturer about consumers","After sales service to the consumer","Useful information to the customers on the benefits and uses of the product","Useful information about market trends and finance to the manufacturer"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Liquidation of a limited liability company implies that the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Company may not pay its debt","Debts of the company can only be paid from its own assets","Debts of the company are paid from both business and private funds of the owners","Debts of the company must be paid from  public funds only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One form of business organization which is not motivated solely by the profit objective is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Joint stock company","Private limited company","Co \u0096 operative society","Ordinary partnership"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Import duties will increase total expenditure on&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>imports if the demand for imports is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Elastic","Inelastic","Derived","Infinitely elastic"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The difference between gross national product&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>and net national product is equal to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Gross investment","Net investment","Net foreign income","Capital depreciation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The value of the total output produced within Nigeria by all residents (citizens and non - citizens) is referred to as the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Gross national product","Disposable income","National income","Gross domestic product"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>International and inter-region trade differ primarily because<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Comparative advantage is relevant to the former but not the latter","Products flow across national boundaries","There are different resources supplies among countries of the world","Of regulation from GATT."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Banks aid economic expansion and development by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Being very strict in lending policies","Mobilizing savings for investment lending","Paying interest on deposit accounts","Charging high interest on loans"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The purchasing power of the naira will fall&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The naira is devalued","There is inflation","Workers are retrenched","Government cuts all salaries and wages."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Monetization refers to the ratio of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total transactions to monetary transactions","Monetary assets to total assets","Monetary transactions to total transactions","Money in circulation to total income"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The best way to reduce the supply of money in the economy is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Increase the liquidity ratio","Liberalize access to credit","Decrease treasury bills","Increase the number of bank notes and cheques produced."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The relationship between the value of money and the price level is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Direct","Unpredictable","Diverse","Inverse"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Non-bank financial intermediaries do not<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sell shares","Accept demand deposits","Provide credit facilities","Accept deposits"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the cost of production for a firm continues to increase as its output rises ,the firm is said to be experiencing<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Large scale production","Profit maximization","Economies of scale","Diseconomies of scale."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the fundamental differences between a capitalist and a socialist economy is that while <\/strong><\/p>","options":["The former is characterized by complete  government ownership of resources, the latter is characterized by complete private ownership","In the former, prices act as signals in the allocation of resources, it is the central authority that performs this function in the latter","Taxation Taxes are levied in a capitalist economy, there is not in a socialist economy","Income and wealth are equally distributed in the socialist economy, this is not so in a capitalist economy"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the fundamental differences between a capitalist and a socialist economy is that while <\/strong><\/p>","options":["The former is characterized by complete  government ownership of resources, the latter is characterized by complete private ownership","In the former, prices act as signals in the allocation of resources, it is the central authority that performs this function in the latter","Taxation Taxes are levied in a capitalist economy, there is not in a socialist economy","Income and wealth are equally distributed in the socialist economy, this is not so in a capitalist economy"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The shape of a production possibility frontier is determined by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Returns to scale","Increasing relative cost","Increasing returns to a variable factor","Diminishing return to a fixed factor"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Normative economics deals with<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Facts and not figures","What is and not what shall should be","Value judgment","Facts and figures"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a free market economy, the price system<\/strong><br \/><strong>allocates resources<\/strong><\/p>","options":["To their best alternative uses","To ensure general welfare","To reduce poverty"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a centrally planned economy, the economic<\/strong><br \/><strong>problem of deciding what to produce is<\/strong><br \/><strong>dependent on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A. Average cost","State command","Average profit"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A demand which is positively related to price is<\/strong><br \/><strong>true of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Capital goods","Normal goods","Given goods","Ostentations goods"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm faces diminishing returns when its<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total output diminishes","Average output diminishes","Marginal output diminishes","Marginal revenue diminishes."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Cross elasticity of demand can be mathematically expressed as the<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Percentage change in quantity of commodity X over  Percentage change in quantity of commodity Y","Percentage change in quantity demanded over Percentage change in price","Percentage change in quantity demanded of commodity X over Percentage change in price of commodity Y","Percentage change in quantity demanded Percentage change in income"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Situation in which all inputs are doubled and output also doubles is known as<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Constant proportion","Constant returns","Increasing returns to scale","Constant returns to scale"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>At any given level of output, the total cost of a firm equals the<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal cost plus the average cost","Fixed costs plus its variable cost","Average cost multiplied by its output","Economic costs multiplied by variable costs."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main reason for charging interest is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Reward entrepreneurial effort","Redistributes profits","Reward investors for present use of capital","Mobilize more funds for development"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the Keynesian model,<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The demand for money is inversely related to the rate of interest","Investment is indirectly related to the rate of interest","Investment is not related to the rate of interest","The demand for money is directly related to the rate in interest"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>If inflation is anticipated to continue,<\/strong><\/p>","options":["People will lose confidence in goods","Lenders will demand higher interest rates","The growth of full-employment output will be \taccelerated","People will want to hold more money"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Restriction on credit creation by commercial Banks can be effected through<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["An overdraft","Loans and advances","Demand deposits","Liquidity ratio"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Counter trading is an international arrangement whereby<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Goods and services are exchanged in a manner similar to barter","Goods and services are sold on the counter","Cude oil is sold to foreign country","Goods are shipped to countries on which the united nations has placed a trade embargo"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is a direct tax?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Excise tax","Corporate income tax","Highway","Property tax"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The three major groups of government revenue are<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Investments income, direct tax and export","Import duties, excise tax and export duties","Company tax, personal income tax and import duties","Company tax, import duties and excise tax"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A tax on a commodity whose supply is perfectly inelastic is<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Shifted completely on the consumer","Completely borne by the supplier","Divide in the ratio 60 : 40 between the consumer and the supplier","Divided half- and \u0096 half between the producer and the consumer"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Under partnership, investors who have no desires to be actively involved in the day-to-day management of such organizations, are called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Stockbrokers","Sleeping partners","Part-time investors","Ordinary partners"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The cooperatives as a form of business organization differs from partnership by having<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Several  sources  of  capital  for  business financing","Ability to issue preferred stocks to members","Entrenched democratic control in the conduct of business","Established rules and regulations governing the activities of its members"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Stocking small quantities of a variety of goods is a function of the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Manufacturer","Wholesaler","Retailer","Consumer"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the major advantages of public enterprises it that<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["They are highly subsidized","They are the largest employers of labor","Their operations are highly standardized","They take prompt decisions and actions"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major effect of a long distribution chain is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["High retail prices","Scarcity of commodities","Low retail prices","Low producer earnings"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The major function of the wholesaler to his customers is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Breaking of bulk","Offering personal services","Stocking a variety of goods","Providing trans-port facility"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The distribution channel that contributes most to the cost of production is<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Producer-wholesaler-consumer","roducer-retailer-consumer","Producer-retailer-consumer","Producer-wholesaler-retailer-consumer"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The law of comparative advantage states that a&nbsp;country should specialize in the production of a commodity<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["For which local demand is greatest","In which its opportunity cost is lower than that of the trade partner","For which foreign demand is greatest","For which there is abundant supply of raw materials"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>By using exchange controls, a country tries to eliminate a balance of payments deficit by<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Limited her imports to its currency value of exports","Reducing the nations domestic price level","Limiting her exports to its currency value of exports"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The need to construct a scale of preference is necessitated by<br \/><br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Scarcity of resources","Non\u00ac-availability of factors of production","Scarcity and the need for choice","The need to satisfy wants."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A shift in the production possibility frontier&nbsp;could result from<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A need to satisfy want","Scarcity and need for choice","Scarcity of resources","Non-availability of factors of production."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The primary problem of economics is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["To obtain a more equitable distribution of money income","Production of a given output with the lowest cost combination of factors of production","Adoption of capital-intensive technology","Increasing the quantity of the fixed factors of production"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>If one orange cost #20 and one kilogram of bear cost #400, the opportunity cost of one kilogram of bear is<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["#350","400 oranges","20 oranges","4 oranges"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In economics life, choice among alternative depends on the<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Income of the decision maker","Scarcity of resources","Scale of preference of the decision maker","Status of the decision maker"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given an original price of #400 per kilogram of rice and a change in price of #20, and given the quality purchased at the old price as 10kg and a change in quantity as 5kg after the price changed the elasticity is equal to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["5","10.8","10","0.80"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>For normal goods the income elasticity of demand is<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Positive","Negative","Zero","Infinite"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>An increase in supply will lower price unless<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Supply is perfectly elastic","Demand is perfectly elastic","It is followed by a reduction in demand","Demand is highly inelastic"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Air is essential to life but commands no price! Diamond is not essential to life but commands a high price! This is the paradox of <br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Shift","Value","Abundance","Scarcity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Average fixed cost is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Average total cost less the sum of average variable cost","Half the cost of all cost","Total fixed cost divided by the level of output","Total fixed cost plus marginal cost"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The average production of labor in given period is obtained by dividing the <br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Number of workers by the total product","Total product by the numbers of hours actually worked","Change in total product by the change in total numbers of workers","Total product by the numbers of workers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following best describes the product function?<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["It indicates the best output to produce","It relates Naira input to Naira output","It relates physical Output to physical input","It indicates the best way to combine factors to produce any given output"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following factors enhance the ability of commercial banks to create money<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Reduction in the reserve ratio","Leakage of cash out of the banking system","Excess reserves","Insistence on collateral security"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In any economy, what is used as money is determined by<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Government acceptance of a commodity Standard","Government acceptance of an inconvertible paper standard","Laws and customs"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The rate of which money changes hands is known as the<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Rate of inflation","Velocity of transaction","Velocity of money","Velocity of circulation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Merchant banks perform all the following functions EXCEPT<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Raising of capital for industry","Provision of current account facility","Management of investment portfolios","Provision of credit for overseas trade"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Export &ndash;promotion policy is primarily concern with the<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Processing of raw materials to increase their value","Making of international route save for export commodities","Production in the number of imported items","Encouragement of the production of export commodities"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>If birth rate is constant and death is declines, population<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Falls","Expands","Stabilizes","Oscillate"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The higher the dependency ratio, the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Larger the proportion of the employed relative to the unemployed","Smaller the proportion of the active labor force relative to the inactive","Smaller the number of non-working age groups relative to the active labor force","Lower the birth rate"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The age distribution of a countries population is of economics importance because it affects the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Pattern of expenditures","Size of the army","Optimum size of firms","Location of industries"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is NOT a goal of modern budget?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The control of inflation","The reduction in income inequality","The shift of all resources from the private to the public sector","Economic development"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The ultimate objective of economics is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Make the best use of scarce resources","Decide under what circumstances in the economy","Organize production at the lowest cost","Make effort to understand how the economic works"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the advantages of partnership over a sole proprietorship is that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Is the most popular form of business organization","The partner can easily withdraw from the business","It makes an increase in the capital of the business possible","There is no limit to the number of people who may bring in capital"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is NOT a type of business ownership?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Debenture holding","Private company","Partnership","Joint stock venture"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A limited liability company is usually owned by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["An individual","A government","Shareholders","Two or more partners"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A modern corporation is owned by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Debenture holders","Ordinary shareholders","Preference shareholders","Creditors"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major short coming of a sole proprietorship form of business is lack of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Working capital","Patronage","Continuity","Market"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the event of liquidation of a private limited liability company, the shareholders liability is limited to their total<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Income from all sources","Family assets","Collateral offers for bank loans","Investment in the company"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is likely to reduce a surplus in the balance of payment of a country?<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Devaluation","Export promotion","Increase tariff on imports","Currency appreciation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is a tariff?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Limit on the amount of good which can be imported","Interest rate on foreign loans","Government payment to domestic producers for exports","Tax on imported goods"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The best method to curb inflation in Nigeria is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A. Reduce importation of commodities","Increase the general level of production","Reduce the volume of money supply","Set up price control boards"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A bank is said to be distressed when it<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Is unable to deal with the central bank","Has a low capital base","Has low level of deposits","Experience serious liquidity crisis"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most important attribute of money is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Homogeneity","Relative scarcity","Divisibility","General acceptability"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a market economy, the question of what, how and for whom to produce are solved by the<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Planning committee","Government","Price mechanism","Elected representative of the people"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic goods are termed scarce goods when they are<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Not available in sufficient quantities to satisfy  all wants for them","Not produced in sufficient quantities to satisfy the effective demand for them","Of high quality","Of primary importance in satisfying the needs of a society"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Macroeconomics is the study of economic science from the point of view of <br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Resource markets or production units","Individual producers of consumers","Aggregate or general economy","Companies or individual firms."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The demand and supply equations for a commodity are given respectively as D = 20 &ndash; &frac12;P, S = 8 + &frac14;P Recalling that at equilibrium D = S, the equilibrium price (p) and quantity (Q) can be obtained as<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["P = 12; Q = 16","P = 14; Q = 10","P = 12; Q = 14","P = 16; Q = 12"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A commodity is said to have a derived demand when the commodity<\/strong><\/p>","options":["And another have joint demand","Is demanded because of what it can help to produce","Is demanded for different purposes","Has inelastic demand"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following changes in equilibrium in equilibrium price and quantity is as a result of an upward shift in the market demand for a commodity?<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Both the price and quantity rise","The price falls and the quantity rises","The price rises and the quantity falls","Both the price and the quantity fell"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following Best describes the production function?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It indicates the best production output to produce","It relates naira inputs to naira outputs","It relates physical outputs to physical inputs","It indicates the best way to combine factors  to produce any given output"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The Law of diminishing returns begins to operate when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total product begins to rise","Total product begins to fall","Marginal product begins to fall","Marginal product begins to rise"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Total fixed cost measures the cost of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["All plant and machinery","All assets where quantity cannot be varied in the short-run","All assets on which the firm has control","Property owned by the firm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The output on which total revenue equals total cost is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Profit-maximizing output","Break-even level output","Loss-minimizing output","Least-cost output"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The total money in circulation includes cash<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Owned by banks, the government and the non-bank public","And current account balance owned by the non- bank public","And current account balance owned by banks and the non-bank public","Owned by banks and non-bank public"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>To reduce the high rate of inflation in the economy, Government should<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Increase taxes and have a budget surplus","Increase taxes and have a budget deficit","Decrease taxes and have budget deficit","Decrease taxes and have a balanced budget"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The money market is a financial market that specializes in the provision of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Short-term loans and advances","Medium-term loans","Long-term loans","Venture capital for development project"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Foreign exchange&nbsp; rate&nbsp; in&nbsp; a&nbsp; free &nbsp;market&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>economy<\/strong>&nbsp;<strong>is determined by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The government","The central bank","Demand and supply","Commercial banks"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The primary objective of all international economic organizations is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Promote\tinternational economic cooperation for the mutual benefit of all  members","Enforce structural adjustment programmes  on less developed countries","Encourage exports from the developed to the less developed countries"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The money which government spends yearly for the maintenance of its schools is<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Used only for wages and salaries"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In order to raise more revenue for a certain period, government should impose higher&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>taxes on goods whose demand is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Elastic","Inelastic","Perfectly elastic","Unitary elastic"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is the major function of the wholesaler?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Bulk breaking","Provision of useful information to the manufacturer on products","Provision of after sales service to consumer","Provision of warehousing facility"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The type of business finance that entitles the holder to a fixed rate of dividend is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Preferred stock","Common stock","Debenture","Bank loan"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>When public enterprises<\/strong>&nbsp;<strong>becomes&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>commercialized it means that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The product of the enterprises are further  subsidized","They are expected to operate with the  primary aim of making profit","The government has decided to divest itself  of such enterprises","The staff of the enterprises will be laid off"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The best channel of distribution of baked bread is through<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Wholesalers to retailer then to consumer","Direct sales to the consumer","Wholesalers to consumer","Retailer to consumer"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following situation can give rise to conomic problems?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Unlimited human wants","Wants of varying importance","Limited means available for satisfying wants","Means used in different ways"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The shares that must be redeemed first at liquidation of a company are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Preference shares","Non-voting ordinary shares","Ordinary shares","Debentures"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>When a nation is experiencing balance of payments surplus it is in a better position to<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Increase its foreign exchange reserves","Increase its liabilities to foreigners","Reduce its foreign exchange reserves","Devalue its national currency"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is a good example of invisible&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>item on balance of payments account?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Shipping an aviation\t  \tBullion","Exports and  imports","Merchandise","Bullion"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Deficit financing is mostly facilitated by the existence of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Stock exchange market","Commercial bank","Central bank","Capital market"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following programme in the monetary sector is aimed at enhancing the banking habit of the rural area?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The deregulation of the banking system","The increase in the number of merchant bank","The community banking scheme","The deregulation of interest rate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Inflation in the Nigeria economy may be fueled by increase in<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The dollar price of crude oil","The sale company share","Government expenditure","Sale of government bond"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Monetary policy aimed at reducing demand pull inflation in the country may be carried out through<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Increase in taxation of private companies, public corporation and private individuals","Increase in cash reserve ratio of commercial banks and the sales of government securities","Decrease in government expenditure on education","Direct price control in the market place"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Scale of preference refers to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Consumers preference for luxurious goods","The household monthly income","List of goods and services in order of priority","Budget preparation without paying due regard to priority"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>For an economy which last year produced only two commodities X and Y, the real cost of the quantity of X which it produced can be measured by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Amount of X It could not produce","Amount of Y it produced","Total amount of Y it could have produced","Extra amount of Y it could have produced"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The middle men in the chain of distribution are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Wholesalers and retailers","Manufacturers and consumers","Consumers and wholesalers","Retailers and Consumers"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One factor which influences the slope of a non-linear demand curve for a commodity is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Price of the commodity","Quantity of the commodity demanded","Availability of substitutes","Availability of complements"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given that the total cost is 1000, total variable cost is 2500 and the output 100 units. The average cost of producing one unit is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["60","45","35","30"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The value of the multiplier depends on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["MPC and a level of income","Level of personal income","Level of personal savings","Government policy and MPC"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>External diseconomies of scale results from excessive growth of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The whole industry","Some sectors of the industry","External factors","Internal factors"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>A country with over-valued currency will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Expect balance of payments surplus","Have increased demand for her exports","Increase her foreign reserve","Decrease her foreign reserve"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the short run, a firm&rsquo;s marginal cost curve above the point of shut-down is its<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Demand curve","Supply curve","Revenue curve","Cost curve"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a planned economy, the emphasis on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Public ownership and control","Prices and competition","Individual choices and decisions","Private ownership and control"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>To compare the standard of living among nations, the most widely used economic indicator is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Real domestic output","Real gross national income","Real per capital income","Per capital nominal income"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>When the importation of a commodity is limited to a definite quantity, the trade control means used is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Exchange control","Tax relief","Devaluation","Quotas"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm operating at full capacity will experience rising short-run costs when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Prices of its variable inputs rise","Prices of its variable inputs fall","There is change in management","Labour productivity increases"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The distinction between onshore and offshore operations lies in the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Location of sites","Output generated","Size of production","Techniques of production"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The burden of a government tax on a commodity whose demand is inelastic will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Be borne only by the government","Fall more heavily on consumers","Be shared equally between consumers and producers","Fall more heavily on producers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major advantage of industrialization is that it<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Leads to self-reliance","Curbs inflation","Leads to growth and development","Improves the terms of trade"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm operating at full capacity will have a<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Perfectly inelastic supply curve","Perfectly elastic supply curve","Fairly elastic supply curve","Fairly inelastic supply curve"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The movement of people from rural to urban areas affects the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Occupational distribution of population","Sex distribution of population","Geographical distribution of population","Age distribution of population"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The export-promotion strategy is aimed at producing<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Consumer goods originally imported","Machinery for industries","More goods for exports","More goods of domestic consumption"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Suppose that the equilibrium price of an article is N500 but the government fixes the price by law at N400, the supply will be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The same as the equilibrium supply","Greater than the equilibrium supply","Less than the equilibrium supply","Determined later by the government"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not a direct tax?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Company income tax","Capital tax","Purchase tax","Personal Income Tax"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The process by which West African countries attempt to reduce the import of manufactured goods by encouraging firms to produce theses at home is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Industrialization","Export promotion","Import substitution","Export substitution"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic principles of co-operative societies are those of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Active participation of capitalists in the affairs of co-operative societies","Worker ownership and owner control","Sole proprietorship","Partnership"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Foreign exchange control in Nigeria is administered by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["United Bank for Africa","Union Bank of Nigeria","First Bank of Nigeria","Central Bank of Nigeria"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The rate of exchange between a domestic and a foreign currency is defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Terms of trade","Domestic currency price of a unit of the foreign currency","Foreign currency price of gold","Domestic currency price of gold"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A perfect example of a public good is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Air","Education","Defense","Transport"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A school girl who needs a book and a mirror, each costing five naira decides to purchase the book instead of the mirror since she cannot pay for the two at the same time. Determine the real cost of her cost.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The five naira she spent on the book","Five naira real cash value","The mirror","The book"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A system in which the means of production is held in trust for the people by government is known as a<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Social economy","Capitalist economy","Subsistence economy","Mixed economy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm determines its profits when it studies its<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal cost","Average cost","Total cost","Average cost relative to price in the market"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given that the elasticity of demand for a commodity is 2.5, the percentage change in the quantity demanded as a result of 10% change in its price is.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.25","0.40","4.00","25.00"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the major consequences of urban-biased development programs in Nigeria is that they<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Led to rapid rural-urban migration","Led to unprecedented urban wealth","Transformed rural areas into urban centres","Increased the level of specialized manpower in the cities"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>An increase in discount rate is an indication of a central banks intention to pursue<\/strong><\/p>","options":["An expansionary monetary policy","A disciplined monetary policy","A dynamic monetary policy","A contractionary monetary policy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the problems arising from the localization of industries is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["High prices of output","The exportation of output","The scarcity of foreign exchange","Structural unemployment"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>An important factor hindering the rapid development of the industrial sector in Nigeria is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Rural-urban migration","Excessive demand for finished products","Inadequate infrastructural facility","The dominance of the oil sector"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic goods are termed scarce goods when they are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Not available in sufficient quantities to satisfy all wants for them","Not purchased in sufficient quantities to satisfy the effective demand for them","Of high quantity","Of primary importance in satisfying needs of a society"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The demand of a commodity is affected by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The consumer of the commodity","The price of the commodity alone","The price of the commodity, income of the consumer, prices of other commodities and preferences of the consumer","Government policy"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The demand curve can be derived from<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The total utility curve","The cardinal utility theory","The marginal curve","All of the above"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic idea behind the brand differentiation under the imperfect market arrangement is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Stimulate demand for rival product","Create demand for the particular product","Enable the product to penetrate the market","Enable the product to compete with other products"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>It is important to measure the national income of a country because<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is a major determinant of a standard of living","It reveals hazards of development like pollution and congestion","It reveals the distribution of the citizens\u0092 saving in foreign bank","Its size determines the extent of political stability"],"answerIndex":"0","examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Consumption plus investment plus government purchases plus net exports make up<\/strong><\/p>","options":["National income","Net national income","Net national product","National product"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The role of the central bank in the economic development of Nigeria is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Use cheques and bank drafts to facilitate business transactions","Maintain a stable price system","Give short and medium term loans to the public","Give financial and technical advice to customers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The average tax rate is defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total tax rate less the marginal tax rate","The tax rate which applies to additional value of income","The ratio of the total taxes paid to total income","Marginal tax rate for being progressive"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is a good example of invisible item, on balance of payments account?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Shipping and aviation","Exports and imports","Merchandise","Bullion"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic decisions are taken<\/strong><\/p>","options":["At the margin","At once as consumption goes on","At the beginning of events","At the level of the household"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>If units of a variable factor are increasingly added to a fixed factor and the marginal physical product keeps increasing, production is said to be taking place under conditions of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Increasing returns to the variable factor","Fixed cost less its variable cost","Constant returns to the variable factor","External economies of scale"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Short run period in production is a period too short for a firm to be able to change its<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Scale of production","Total revenue","Variable inputs","Total outputs"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm&rsquo;s shut-down point is reached when the average revenue fails to cover the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal cost","Average fixed cost","Average total cost","Average variable cost"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The need to construct a scale of preference is necessitated by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The need to satisfy wants","Scarcity and the need for choice","Scarcity of resources","Non-availability of factors of production"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>If at 10k per kg, 1000kg of yam were purchased and at 5k per kg, 1500kg were purchased, the resultant point elasticity of demand is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.33","0.0001","1","10,000"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a wage increase is granted to a cement manufacturer&rsquo;s worker, the supply curve of cement will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Move to the right","Move to the left","Move to the opposite side","Move to nowhere"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The elasticity of supply of perishable goods is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Inelastic","Elastic","Unitary","Zero"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The average product of labour in a given period is obtained by dividing the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Number of workers by the total product","Total product by the number of hours actually worked","Change in total product by the change in the total number of workers","Total product by the number of workers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A possible factor which limits the extent of growth of a firm is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Existence of a monopoly","Bureaucratic delays in decision making","Use of by-products","Unwillingness to share ownership and control"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major difference between a state-owned enterprise and a private enterprise is that the former<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Is not expected to cover its cost of production while the latter is","Is not always expected to maximize profits while the latter is","Has shareholders while latter does not","Has a board of directors while the latter does not"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main handicap of sole proprietorship is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Limited liability","Lack of technical know-how","Low profit margin","Inadequate capital"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Taxes and government expenditures are instruments of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Monetary policy","Tax policy","Economic policy","Fiscal policy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>If C stands for consumption, I for investment, X for exports and M for imports, then national income is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["C + I + X + M","C + I + X \u0096 M","C + I \u0096 X + M","C + I + X"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A capital market differs from the money market in that in the former<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Loan sought is long-term","Loan repayment is guaranteed","Loan sought is short-termed","The percentage of interest charged is more"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The money market is a financial market that specializes in the provision of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Short-term loans and advances","Medium-term loans","Long-term loans","Venture capital for the development projects"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>There is an improvement in the terms of trade of a country if<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A large quantity of exports is given to obtain a unit of imports","The volume of exports is greater than the volume of imports","A small quantity of exports is given up to obtain a unit of imports","The value of exports is greater than the value of imports"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A country with over-valued currency will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Decrease her foreign reserve","Have increased demand for her exports","Increase her foreign reserve","Expect balance of payments surplus"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>In an agricultural economy, a poor harvest which diverts demand away from industrial goods leads to trade cycle by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Leading to an increase in labour\/capital ratio","Leading to constant labour\/capital ratio","Leading to increased capital investment","Leading to an increase in capital\/output ratio"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The production possibility curve can be used to explain the underlying concepts of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Scale of preference and choice","Opportunity cost and choice","Wants and means","Opportunity cost and scale of preference"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the increase in the price of yams is used to estimate the inflation rate, this is an example of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Deductive reasoning","Inductive reasoning","Normative reasoning","Positive reasoning"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>54, 35, 62, 79, 83, 36, 62, 42, 62, 42.Calculate the mean<\/strong><\/p>","options":["45.5","55.7","55.8","65.8"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>54, 35, 62, 79, 83, 36, 62, 42, 62, 42<\/strong><br \/><strong>Calculate the modal score<\/strong><\/p>","options":["36","42","54","62"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major determinant of demand for a luxury good is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The price of the good","Price of other goods","The income of consumers","Taste and fashion"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>As long as marginal utility is positive, total utility must be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Negative","Increasing","Zero","Decreasing"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the factors affecting the supply of manufactured good is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Weather","Technology","Consumer tastes","Availability of inputs"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>An upward movement along the same supply curve results in<\/strong><\/p>","options":["An increase in supply","A decrease in price","A decrease in quantity supplied","An increase in quantity supplied"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>An example of an indirect tax is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Profit tax","Sales tax","Capital gain tax","Poll tax"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>An example of an indirect tax is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Profit tax","Sales tax","Capital gain tax","Poll tax"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major consideration in locating a cement factory is the availability of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Skilled labour","Power","Infrastrutural facilities","Limestone"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The activities of the oil and gas industries are classified into<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Exploration and transportation","Upstream and downstream","Discovery and extraction","Onshore and offshore"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Joint-stock companies can raise funds from<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The money market","The capital market","Various sources","Government"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>To protect farmers during a bumper harvest, the government usually<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sets a maximum price","Releases products from the buffer stock","Sells the excess to consumers","Sets a minimum price"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Contractionary monetary policy is used to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Control inflation","Bridge the deflationary gap","Expand the output level","Deregulate the economy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The output approach to measuring national income is based on the computation of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Final output","Factor cost","Value added","Profits earned"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Developments outside a given firm which reduce the firm&rsquo;s costs are called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Internal economies","External economies","External diseconomies","Optimum effects"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>If X represents the factors of production and Y represents the price factor, which of the following sets of association is correct?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["(land, rent), (capital, wage), (labour, profit)","(land, interest), (capital, profit), (labour, wage)","(land, wage), (capital, interest), (land, rent)","(land, rent), (capital, interest), (labour, wages)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>If at 10k per kg, 1000kg of yam were purchased and at 5k per kg, 1500kg were purchased, the resultant point elasticity of demand is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.33","0.0001","1","10,000"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A situation in which all inputs are doubled and output also doubles is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Constant proportions","Constant returns","Increasing returns to scale","Constant returns to scale"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic goods are termed scarce goods when they are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Not available in sufficient quantities to satisfy all wants for them","Not produced in sufficient quantities to satisfy the effective demand for them","Of high quality","Of primary importance in satisfying the needs of society"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following situations will give rise to economic problems?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Unlimited human wants","Wants of varying importance","Limited means for satisfying wants","Means used in different ways"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Population <\/strong><br \/><strong>(Million) Food Prouduction<\/strong><br \/><strong>(Million tones)<\/strong><br \/><strong>50 220<\/strong><br \/><strong>70 210<\/strong><br \/><strong>90 225<\/strong><br \/><strong>100 275<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>In the table above, what is the optimum population in million?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["50","70","90","100"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>An accurate census is important to a country because it helps<\/strong><\/p>","options":["In solving unemployment problem","To ensure equitable population distribution relative to natural resources","In deciding on creation of more local government","In providing sound basis for formulating development policy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Circular flow of income defines the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Relationship between end and means in the economic system","Allocation of income to various members of the household","Flow of goods, services and money amongst the various macro-section of the economy","Microeconomic relationships in economic analysis"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the long run, all production factors are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Fixed","Semi-fixed","Variable","Semi-variable"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The advantages which firms obtain directly from expanding their operations are referred to as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Internal economies of scale","External economies of scale","Economies of localization","Economies of resources allocation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The effect of changes in the condition of demand on a demand schedule with the price constant is a<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Movement along the demand curve","Deflation of the demand curve","Hyperbola formation by the demand curve","Shift of the demand curve"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a demand curve that intersects a price inelastic supply curve shifts rightward.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The equilibrium price and quantity increases","Only the price will increase","Only the quantity will increase","The price will remain constant"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The average product of labour in a given period is obtained by dividing the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Number of workers by the total product","Total product by the number of hours actually worked","Change in total product by change in the total number of workers","Total product by the number of workers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the cost of production for a firm continues to increase as its output rises, the firm is said to be experiencing<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Large scale production","Profit maximization","Economies of scale","Diseconomies of scale"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following best describes the production function?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It indicates the best output to produce","It relates naira inputs to naira outputs","It relates physical outputs to physical inputs","It indicates the best way to combine factors to produce any given output"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given perfect competition in the capital market, the opportunity cost of capital is adequately reflected by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Interest rate","Returns on capital","Alternate capital forgone","Shadow price of foreign exchange"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following reward is associated with enterpreneurship as a factor of production?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Salaries","Profits","Interests","Rents"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a market economy, the question of what, how and for whom to produce are solved by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Elected representative of the people","Planning committee","Price mechanism","Government"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>At any given level of output, a firms total variable cost equals<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total cost less marginal cost","Total cost less total fixed cost","Total cost less average cost","Average variable cost and marginal variable cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>At any given level of output, a firms total variable cost equals<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total cost less marginal cost","Total cost less total fixed cost","Total cost less average cost","Average variable cost and marginal variable cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Age groups (years) Distribution (%)<\/strong><br \/><strong>Above 60 30<\/strong><br \/><strong>15 &ndash; 60 45<\/strong><br \/><strong>0 - 14 25<\/strong><br \/><strong>The estimated dependency ratio of the population shown above is:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["11:9","9:11","7:3","3:7"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following factors is NOT responsible for the rural\/urban drift in Nigeria?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The infrastructural facilities in the cities","Declining fertility of rural farmlands","Rural electrification programme","Higher living standards in urban areas"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The necessity of choice is due to the fact that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Human wants are insatiable","Customers like to maximize satisfaction","Resources are abundant","Consumers are selective"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is meant by labour supply?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Number of people in working population","Number of men and hours they work","Number of hours during which the middle-aged persons work","Number of workforce multiplied by the hours they worked"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>&nbsp;Any payment to a factor of production in excess of what is necessary to keep its present employment is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Real income","Profit","Economic rent","Real wage"],"answerIndex":"0","examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The market where there are many differentiated products is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Monopoly","Perfect competition","Monopolistic competition","Oligopoly"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the dangers of localization of industries is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Residual unemployment","Mass unemployment","Structural unemployment","Cyclic unemployment"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>In commercial banking, an account from which a customer cannot withdrew money instantly is a<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Demand deposit account","Time deposit account","Special deposit account","Saving deposit account"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Banks can create more money by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Increasing their cash ratio with the central bank","Issuing more bank cheques","Accepting more deposits from customers","Lending out money from customers\u0092 deposits"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most important factor in ensuring economic development is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Effective mobilization of domestic savings","Presence of foreign account","Formulation of appropriate government policies","Attraction of foreign aids and grants"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Scarcity in economics means that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Human wants are limitless","The economy has very few resources","The economy can scarcely produce anything","Resources are limited"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Air is essential to life but commands no price! Diamond is not essential to life but commands a high price! This is the paradox of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Thrift","Value","Abundance","Scarcity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economies of scale operate only when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal cost is falling with input","Average cost is falling with input","Fixed cost is variable","Variable cost is less than fixed cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Efficiency in production involves<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Reducing the size of workforce","Producing a given output with the lowest cost combination of factors of production","Adoption of capital intensive technology","Increasing the quantity of the fixed factor of production"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>An effect of inflation is that it &hellip;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Discourages trade by barter","Favours debtors at the expense of creditors","Increases the real income of salary earners","Increases the value of a country\u0092s exports"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>The migration of young people from rural areas in Nigeria should help to raise the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Standard of living in the urban areas","Total productivity of labour in the rural areas","Marginal productivity of labour in the rural areas","Marginal productivity of labour in the urban areas"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>A modern corporation is owned by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Debenture holders","Ordinary shareholders","Preference shareholders","Creditors"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the most important factors that should be considered in the location of an industry is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Nearness to  the financial centre","Assured patronage by government","Availability of inputs and market","Availability of adequate security"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is the term used to describe a policy aimed at promoting the local production of goods which are usually imported?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Deregulation","Import substitution","Tariff reduction","Backward integration"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Progressive tax structure is designed to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Take more from the income of the poor","Take more from the income of the rich","Take equal proportion of income from both the rich and the poor","Reduce the problems emanating from tax imposition"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>The use of legally permissible means to reduce tax liabilities is known as tax<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Evasion","Avoidance","Relief","Exemtion"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>The greatest proportion of government revenue in Nigeria comes from<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Export of raw materials","Income taxes on individuals and businesses","Custom duties and excise taxes","Loans and grants from industrially advanced countries"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Privatization of government owned companies means the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Relinqishing of government\u0092s equity","Recapitalization of private individuals","Joint participation of government and private individuals","Commercialization and deregulation of the economy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Gains from trade depend on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Comparative advantage","Absolute advantage","Distributive cost advantage","Absolute cost advantage"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>A country&rsquo;s import price index by 1995 was 50 and her index of export price was 70, calculate the terms of trade<\/strong><\/p>","options":["20%","71%","120%","140%"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"}]